Suhail Ghafoor

J (602) 666 8440

in /in/phoenix-effect

phoenixeffect.me

Suhail.Ghafoor@asu.edu

Professional Summary

I am a highly skilled technology professional with skills that range from building websites to managing systems and network security. I have a diverse work experience which includes positions at large corporations, small charities, as well as freelance projects.

Overview

Expertise

- Web development
- Objected-Oriented Programming
- Database design and management
- Video editing and streaming
- Graphics design
- Computer repair and maintenance
- UI/UX designing
- Binary analysis
- Computer network and security
- Waterfall and Agile development
- Task automation

Skills

OS Windows, Mac, Ubuntu, CentOS, Debian, iOS

Frameworks Wordpress, WooCommerce,

Drupal, HuGo, Django, OpenScholar

Tools Amazon AWS, Slurm, Pantheon, Webmin, Salesforce, ExactTarget, Mailchimp, Sendgrid, Zapier, rest API, EmailOnAcid

Software Adobe Fireworks, Premiere Pro, After Effects, Eclipse, Jetbrains software, XCode, VMWare, Hyper-V, iptables

Languages PHP, javascript, jquery, ajax, websockets, CSS, Java, C, C++, Prolog, Lisp, Go, NodeJS, JSON, XML, Python, Assembly, AppleScript, Bash, SQL, LaTeX, OCaml, Scheme, Swift, Git, Markdown

Work History

The Center for Evolution & Medicine at Arizona State University

2015-Present

CEM is a research and education based center at Arizona State University whose mission is to expand the impact of evolutionary medicine in order to improve human health. I have worked extensively as a web developer, program coder, AV and computer systems support technician, and consulted on software and technology acquisitions.

Computing

- Assist PI, researchers, and staff with new hardware and software purchases
- Manage inventory of all computing equipment
- Serve as tier 1-2 support for all computing issues at CEM
- Ensure all department technologies are compliant with ASU computing, data, and security policies.
 Liaison for CEM for population genomics computing cluster.
- Regular repair and maintenance of computing equipment in three CEM meeting rooms
- Arrange requirements for special events like conference phones, video streams, video conference, and response systems

Online Presence and Marketing

- Create and apply graphics for social media and ASU events platform
- Maintain the department's YouTube channel
- Migrated newsletter platform from MailChimp to ASU's marketing cloud account
- Manage subscribers and mailing list

Web Development

Stone Lab (stone.lab.asu.edu)

- Redesigned frontend and update of backend
- Migrated the website to new servers that comply with ASU IT security policies
- Regular maintenance and update of content on the website

Evolution Medicine Review (evmedreview.com)

- Redesigned frontend and set up analytics on the website
- Maintenance and security updates
- Added a new email subscription system

Molecular Epidemiology Analytics Core (meac.asu.edu)

- Redesigned frontend and set up analytics on the website
- Maintenance and security updates
- Added a new email subscription system

EvMedEd (evmeded.org)

- Wrote script to populate content's metadata in Airtable
- Designed website according to ASU's brand and security guidelines
- Integrated the website with ASU's single sign on system

Center For Evolution and Medicine (evmed.asu.edu)

- Developed and deployed CEM website using technologies that comply with ASU's brand standards
- Ongoing maintenance and content updates
- Imported content from old website to new
- Programmed custom response system for events and connected them with ASU events
- Added ASU's business analytics to website
- Added a custom email subscription form that lets users subscribe to CEM's multiple email lists

PMLN - Online Media Manager

2012-2015

PMLN is a political party in Pakistan that won the 2013 election. I assisted with the following for their campaign

- Set live streaming of political events on the internet for thousands of viewers
- Issued press releases to newspaper and TV channels
- Redesigned and developed party's website for political campaign
- Created hub on the website to download campaign material for supporters and created forms for joining the party
- Designed newsletter templates
- Bought and installed custom hardware to let the prime minister do a live QA session on social media
- Developed survey development for quantitative research among supporters

Gamers Den - System Support (Volunteer Position)

2005-2007

Gamers den was the largest gaming café in Islamabad (Pakistan) in existence for 6 years

- Diagnosed computer and network issues
- Set up new computers and installed relevant software

Freelance and Contract Projects

2008-2018

I have freelanced for several years on projects that challenged and pushed my professional skill development and growth. I have listed a few of my notable projects below:

Project #1 Lab Safety Trainer

2018-19

Scenario based lab safety training app for ASU, coded in Django and ReactJS and linked with ASU's single sign on system.

Project #2 Pkpolitics

2008-15

Pkpolitics was the biggest political discussion forum of Pakistan during its peak in 2009. It provided a platform for overseas Pakistani citizens and supporters to watch political commentary TV shows and engage in political discussions before the era of YouTube.

- Recorded and uploaded political TV shows on the website
- Installed and maintained custom recording and video encoding hardware
- Wrote custom scripts for automated recording and uploading videos
- Installed and maintained UPS for servers
- Generated discount coupons for membership on website for journalists
- Cameraman for exclusive interviews with politicians
- Redesigned the website 3 times over 7 years
- Designed custom charts to announce election results online
- Data entry to convert hand written election results to Excel
- Streamed breaking news on website
- Backed up and archived videos
- Coded a custom twitter bot for website that displays the trending topics in Pakistan on website and tracked historical trends

Project #3 IADSR

2010-14

IADSR is a society of dentists who host an annual conference every year in Pakistan.

- Setup website and conference registration systems
- Designed the logo
- Managed social media accounts
- Provided technology equipment and support for annual conference

Project #4 SA Traders

2014

SA Traders is an electronics shop in Pakistan

Designed, developed, and deployed WordPress website using WooCommerce

Project #5 Zubaida Barkat Trust

2013

ZBT is a charity organization that works to teach practical life skills to orphans in Pakistan

Designed, developed, and deployed WordPress website

Project #6 SuchTV

2013

SuchTV is a news channel in Pakistan

Designed custom news and articles for website

Project #7 ToffeeTV

ToffeeTV is a children's website in Pakistan

2013

Created custom video management system

Education

Bachelor of Computer Science 2015-2019

Arizona State University

Bachelor of Applied Psychology 2012-2014

University of the Punjab

Volunteer Work

Undergraduate researcher Aug 2017-Present

Sex Chromosome Lab

Cybersecurity researcher Jun-Aug 2016

CYSIS lab

Certifications

Google web development certification 2017

Public Opinion and Survey Research 2014